Chapter 24. The advocate.
As Quiquake and I are now fairly embarked in this business of whailing,
and as this business of whailing has somehow come to be regarded among
landsmen as a rather unpoetical and disreputable pursuit, therefore I am all
anxiety to convince you, ye landsmen, of the injustice hereby done to us hunters of whales.
In the first place, it may be deemed almost superfluous to establish the fact
that among people at large, the business of whaling is not accounted on a level
with what are called the liberal professions. If a stranger were
introduced into any miscellaneous metropolitan society, it would but
slightly advance the general opinion of his merits, were he presented to the
company as a harpooner, say, and if, in emulation of the naval officers, he
should append the initials SWF, sperm whale fishery, to his visiting card,
such a procedure would be deemed preeminently presuming and ridiculous.
Doubtless one leading reason why the world declines honoring us whalemen is
this. They think that at best our vocation amounts to a butchering sort of
business and that when actively engaged therein we are surrounded by all manner of defilements.
Butchers we are that is true. But butchers also and butchers of the
bloodiest badge have been all the marshall commanders whom the world
invariably delights to honor. And as for the matter of the alleged uncleanliness
of our business, you shall soon be initiated into certain facts hitherto
pretty generally unknown, and which upon the whole will triumphantly plant the
sperm whale ship, at least among the cleanliest things of this tidy earth?
But even granting the charge in question to be true, what disordered slippery
decks of a whale ship are comparable to the unspeakable carry-in of those
battlefields from which so many soldiers return to drink in all ladies plaudits.
And if the idea of peril so much enhances the popular conceit of the
soldier's profession, let me assure you that many a veteran who has freely
marched up to a battery would quickly recoil at the apparition of the sperm
whales vast tale fanning into eddies the air over his head. For what are the
comprehensible terrors of man compared with the interlin terrors and wonders of
God? But though the world scouts at us whale hunters, yet does it unwittingly
pay us the profoundest homage. Yay, in all abounding adoration, for almost all
the tapers, lamps, and candles that burn round the globe burn, as before so many
shrines to our glory. But look at this matter in other lights. Weigh it in all
sorts of scales. See what we whalemen are and have been. Why did the Dutch in
Dwit's time have admirals of their whailing fleets? Why did Louis V 16th of
France at his own personal expense fit out whailing ships from Dunkerk and
politely invite to that town some score or two of families from our own island of Nantucket?
Why did Britain between the years 1750 and 1788 pay her whaleman in bounties of
upwards of 1 million?
And lastly, how comes it that we whalemen of America now outnumber all
the rest of the banded whalemen in the world, sail a navy of upwards of 700
vessels, manned by 18,000 men, yearly consuming $4 million of dollars, the
ships worth, at the time of sailing, $20 million, and every year importing into
our harbors a well-reed harvest of $7 million. How comes all this if there be
not something quissant in wailing? But this is not the half. Look again. I
freely assert that the cosmopolite philosopher cannot for his life point
out one single peaceful influence which within the last 60 years has operated
more potentially upon the whole broad world taken in one aggregate than the
high and mighty business of whailing.
One way and another it has begotten events so remarkable in themselves and
so continuously momentous in their sequential issues that wailing may well
be regarded as that Egyptian mother who bore offspring themselves pregnant from
her womb. It would be a hopeless endless task to catalog all these things. Let a
handful suffice. For many years past, the whale ship has been the pioneer in
feriting out the remotest and least known parts of the earth. She has
explored seas and archipelos which had no chart, where no Cook or Vancouver had
ever sailed. If American and European men of war now peacefully ride in once
savage harbors, let them fire salutes to the honor and glory of the whale ship
which originally showed them the way and first interpreted between them and the
savages. They may celebrate as they will the heroes of exploring expeditions,
your cooks, your cruisensteins, but I say that scores of anonymous captains
have sailed out of Nantucket that were as great and greater than your cook and
your crusian stern. For in their suckerless, empty-handedness, they in
the heathenish shark waters, and by the beaches of unrecorded javelin islands,
battled with virgin wonders and terrors that Cook with all his marines and
musketss would not willingly have dared.
All that is made such a flourish of in old South Sea voyages, those things were
but the lifetime common places of our heroic Nantucketers, often adventures
which Vancouver dedicates three chapters to. These men accounted unworthy of
being set down in the ship's common log.
Ah, the world. Oh, the world. Until the whale fishery rounded Cape Horn, no
commerce but colonial, scarcely any intercourse but colonial was carried on
between Europe and the long line of the opulent Spanish provinces on the Pacific
coast. It was the whalemen who first broke through the jealous policy of the
Spanish crown touching those colonies.
And if space permitted, it might be distinctly shown how from those whalemen
at last eventuated the liberation of Peru, Chile, and Bolivia from the yoke
of old Spain, and the establishment of eternal democracy in those parts. That
great America on the other side of the sphere, Australia, was given to the
enlightened world by the whaleman. After its first blunderborn discovery by a
Dutchman, all other ships long shunned those shores as pestiferously barbarous,
but the whale ship touched there. The whale ship is the true mother of that
now mighty colony. Moreover, in the infancy of the first Australian
settlement, the immigrants were several times saved from starvation by the
benevolent biscuit of the whale ship, luckily dropping an anchor in their
waters. The uncounted isles of all Polynesia confessed the same truth, and
do commercial homage to the whale ship that cleared the way for the missionary
and the merchant, and in many cases carried the primitive missionaries to
their first destinations. If that doublebolted land, Japan is ever to
become hospitable, it is the whale ship alone to whom the credit will be due,
for already she is on the threshold.
But if, in the face of all this, you still declare that whailing has no
aesthetically noble associations connected with it, then I am ready to
shiver 50 lances with you there, and unhorse you with a split helmet every time.
The whale has no famous author and whailing no famous chronicler. You will
say the whale no famous author and whailing no famous chronicler. Who wrote
the first account of our Leviathan? Who but mighty Job? And who composed the
first narrative of a whailing voyage?
Who but no less a prince than Alfred the Great, who with his own royal pen took
down the words from author, the Norwegian whale hunter of those times?
And who pronounced our glowing eulogy in Parliament? Who but Edmund Burke?
True enough. But then whale men themselves are poor devils. They have no
good blood in their veins. No good blood in their veins. They have something
better than royal blood there. The grandmother of Benjamin Franklin was
Mary Moral. Afterwards by marriage, Mary Fulier, one of the old settlers of
Nantucket and the ancestrous to a long line of folders and harpineers, all kith
and kin to the noble Benjamin, to this day darting the barbed iron from one
side of the world to the other. Good again. But then all confess that somehow
whailing is not respectable.
Whailing not respectable. Whailing is imperial. By the old English statutory
law, the whale is declared a royal fish.
Oh, that's only nominal. The whale himself is never figured in any grand
imposing way. The whale never figured in any grand imposing way. In one of the
mighty triumphs given to a Roman general upon his entering the world's capital,
the bones of a whale brought all the way from the Syrian coast were the most
conspicuous object in the symbol procession.
Footnote. See subsequent chapters for something more on this head. End of footnote.
Grant it since you cite it, but say what you will, there is no real dignity in
whailing. No dignity in wailing. The dignity of our calling, the very heavens
attest. Satus is a constellation in the south. No more. Drive down your hat in
the presence of the zar and take it off
to Que. No more. I know a man that in his lifetime has taken 350 whales. I
account that man more honorable than that great captain of antiquity who
boasted of taking as many walled towns.
And as for me, if by any possibility there be any as yet undiscovered prime
thing in me, if I shall ever deserve any real repute in that small but high
hushed world, which I might not be unreasonably ambitious of, if hereafter
I shall do anything that upon the whole a man might rather have done than to
have left undone, if at my death my executives, or more properly my
creditors, find any precious as manuscripts in my desk. Then here I
prospectively ascribe all the honor and the glory to whailing. For a whale ship
was my Yale College and my Harvard.